גוט טאג! Gutt Tag! Today's דף, daf, we are ahead yet again
and I know we'll have to figure out how to deal with
being so far ahead, should be our biggest problem. Anyway, we pick
up on
מ"ט עמוד ב', Mem Tet Amud Bet, 49b. It looks like we
will, God willing, go through דף נ' Daf Nun today. So we
start with the משנה. mishna. We've been now, this פרק perek has
been focused on the prohibition of the נזיר Nazir not becoming טמא,
tamei, but it starts of course with the idea that a נזיר
Nazir can become טמא tamei for מת מצוה, Meis Mitzvah, and we
spent a lot of yesterday and the day before understanding how we
learn that out from the verse, that מת מצוה Meis Mitzvah overrides
the restrictions of a נזיר Nazir and a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
and even when those are piled on one another, going to do
a ברית מילה, Bris Milah, קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, anyway the overriding
nature of מת מצוה, Meis Mitzvah, and then the only interesting question
became the question about priorities about whose קדושה kedusha do you preserve,
protect first if there's some choice to be made. Our משנה mishna
turns to the actual nature of the parameters of the restrictions of
a נזיר Nazir being טמא. tamei. In some way we dealt with
all the restrictions in an earlier פרק, perek, שלשה מינים, Shlosha Minim,
but here we are dealing with more the specific parameters of טומאה.
tumah. To some degree it's a question about what types of things
cause טומאה. tumah. If that were true we could go ahead and
learn major sections of מסכת טהרות, Meseches Taharos, so we will not
be overly focusing on that, but it will be giving us some
of the basic parameters of the amounts of a dead body and
the parts of a dead body and the minimum sizes that cause
טומאה, tumah, but an interesting הלכה halacha that we will see is
that there are a few cases of something that causes טומאת מת,
tummat meis, but nevertheless the נזיר Nazir does not shave his head
as a result of, is not prohibited against, and so there are
some arbitrary things which we learn from tradition, הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha
L'Moshe MiSinai, that even though they cause טומאת מת, tummat meis, are
somehow excluded from this prohibition. And that is very relevant because we
learn the parameters of טומאת כהנים tummas kohanim and the restrictions of
טומאת כהנים tummas kohanim from the restrictions of the נזיר. Nazir. So
those exceptions, although initially some of those exceptions will seem obscure and
irrelevant, there are some that will be relevant, so keep your eye
open for that. Already a question? Yes.
Just trying to bring it to the level of practicality. So I
understand that טומאה tumah for כהן kohen is relevant today. Right. Or
are any of these other טומאות tumos relevant at all in any
fact?
No, unless somebody decides to be a נזיר. Nazir. No. Okay, so
now we take a look at the משנה. mishna. The answer is
no. על אלו טומאות הנזיר מגלח. Al elu tumos hanazir megale'ach. So
the משנה mishna on מ"ט עמוד ב'. Mem Tet Amud Bet. על
אלו טומאות הנזיר מגלח. Al elu tumos hanazir megale'ach. For the following
טומאות tumos are the ones that a נזיר Nazir will shave his
head for, that destroy the current count of the נזירות, nezirus, you
have to bring a קרבן, korban, you have to start again and
so on. על המת ועל כזית מן המת, Al hameis v'al k'zayis
min hameis, on an entire corpse, not even an entire corpse, even
just a כזית k'zayis size of the flesh of the corpse. Okay,
so the amount of כזית k'zayis is, you know when you think
about it, a little ironic because normally we use כזית k'zayis for
an amount for foods, and here, but it also becomes sort of
like a default size, like you know, very often there's a whole
different ranges of minimum sizes, but כזית k'zayis often is assumed to
be like a default even not in the context of food. Anyway,
for whatever reason the tradition here is that even an olive size
of the flesh of a corpse causes טומאת מת, tummat meis, and
טומאת מת באהל, tummat meis b'ohel, I should say the first things
on this list, until we get to the very end there will
be a small second list, are things that cause טומאת מת tummat
meis even if you're under the same roof. Okay, come back to
the bigger קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. There are three ways of conducting
טומאה tumah for a מת: meis: מגע, maga, משא, massa, move, you
know, מגע, maga, משא, massa, and or being אהל. ohel. משא massa
carrying but it's a form of moving or whatever. We won't worry
about some of the differences. And being in the אהל. ohel. אהל
ohel could be under the same roof. It could mean you're on
top of the מת meis or the מת meis is on top
of you. Those are three forms of אהל. ohel. By אהל ohel
the תורה Torah more emphasizes the entire dead body. אדם כי ימות
באהל, Adam ki yamut b'ohel, right, if an אדם adam is מת
באהל. meis b'ohel. I mean it also talks about לכל נפש אדם,
l'chol nefesh adam, other types of טומאה tumah as well, but anyway
to some degree you can conceptually see that what we're trying to
do by טומאת אהל tummat ohel is define really something that's to
some degree a part that's representative of the whole. Like and that's
why there's slightly different שיעורים. shiurim. There are a few small things
that the size is so small and because of the object we're
dealing with that cause טומאה tumah by מגע maga but not in
the אהל. ohel. But the first list are things that causes טומאה
tumah in the אהל. ohel. Okay, yes.
So just so I have a visual image, if I'm in the
basement and the מת meis is in the attic and the floors
in between.
Okay, so that's a good question. That's what all מסכת אהלות Meseches
Oholos is about. There are ways in which if basically there's a
roof on top of the מת meis and there's a טפח tefach
there that the roof is
roofing over
a טפח tefach of an air space, right, not of a vacuum,
what's the word I'm looking for, of a cavity or something. Anyway,
then it stops the טומאה tumah from going through. Okay, however. There
are some cases like some things that are מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah
don't stop the טומאה tumah from going through. The problem about flying
over a cemetery is because there is not a טפח tefach because
it's all just the dirt. Now you might say one minute, the
coffin has a טפח, tefach, but the coffin is a separate הלכה,
halacha, it becomes seen as an extension of the מת, meis, so
it doesn't stop the טומאה. tumah. Okay, but yes, if there is
a roof between and there's a טפח tefach between the roof under
most circumstances that will stop the טומאה tumah from going through.
Look at the down also, upstairs and you go there and,
yeah, but if you're also below it if there... yeah, I mean
there's ways in which it stops, you know, those directions, the entire
מסכת. maseches. Okay. אלו טומאות הנזיר מגלח, Eilu tumeos hanazir m'galeach, על
המת, al hameis, an entire corpse, ועל כזית מן המת, v'al kezayis
min hameis, on just a כזית, kezayis, ועל כזית נצל. v'al kezayis
netzel. Now a כזית kezayis of נצל, netzel, we are going to
see what this means in the גמרא, Gemara, but it basically is
a type of the flesh that has sort of dissolved, decomposed, liquefied
and then it's recongealed. Okay, so basically it has a similar status
as the flesh itself. ועל מלא תרווד רקב, v'al melo torvad rekeve,
and on a ladle-sized spoonful, how much a what
type of ladle are we talking about whatever we'll see in the
גמרא, Gemara, but on a certain quantity of filled with the decomposed
matter of the body. So it's not flesh that liquefied and solidified,
it's more like dust, you know, ashes to ashes, dust to dust,
when it has become dust. Okay, still מטמא? metamei? Yep, we will
see, some of these are like total הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai. No, that would be ashes, that would be אפר, eifer, this
is a natural decomposition. Okay. על שדרה ועל גולגולת, al shidra v'al
gulgoles, on the spinal cord and the skull, whether that means the
combination or either we'll see, ועל אבר מן המת, v'al ever min
hameis, on a full limb of the dead body, and not only
that, ועל אבר מן החי. v'al ever min hachai. Now this is
something you might not have expected, but if a limb falls off
of a person who is alive, that also causes טומאת מת. tumas
meis. So the limb is actually interesting because you know until now
I was saying that these things sort of are representative of the
whole, there's actually a word for that, for an English term, that's
when a part represents the whole, synecdoche, synecdochic, I always get it
mixed up with Schenectady New
York, synecdoche.
Okay, so anyway, here
it's interesting because here the person isn't dead, right, now starting channeling
Monty Python, I'm not dead, anyway the person isn't dead, but you
have a limb, an entire limb is seen as so it's not
representing the whole corpse, but in itself is somehow seen as itself
a type of a מת. meis. So that's particularly interesting.
From your own? Yeah, so meaning you know, let's say you have
God forbid to have an amputation, you could have...
right. Well, I mean, I mean whatever, yeah, there'll be implications, right.
Okay, so anyway, so on a limb that fell off from life,
שיש עליו בשר כראוי. she'yeish alav basar karuy.
Now these ideas of אבר ever means it can't just be the
bones, there has to be enough flesh. How much is enough? So
the basic amount of enough is that if this limb were attached
to the body there would be enough flesh so that the limb
could heal, so that it could like you know it could develop
a scar and heal and whatever, and so that's considered so when
we're thinking about it as a limb, it's not only bone but
also a certain amount of the actual flesh. ועל חצי קב עצמות,
v'al chatzi kav atzamos, on a half of a קב. kav. I
did not look up how much this is. Anyway, but a few
ounces I guess, ounce is actually what, is ounce a volume measurement?
No weight.
Anyway, whatever it is, all these are volume measurements. Anyway, on a
half of a קב kav of bones. Here I want to stop
for a moment because if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, על חצי
קב עצמות, al chatzi kav atzamos, this is the first of the
exceptions that I had mentioned. תוספות Tosafos says first of all, ומיירי
שבאו מרוב מנינו או מרוב בנינו. u'mairi she'bau mi'rov minyano o mi'rov
binyano.
So basically it's not just random bones, it has to be that
you had a certain quantity of bones that either was a majority
of the number of bones in the body or that they was
a majority of the structure of the body. Now that in itself
causes טומאה, tumah, רוב מנין ורוב בנין, rov minyan v'rov binyan, טומאה
באוהל. tumah b'ohel. But let's say then those bones were crushed, okay,
and then you scooped out from that pile of crushed bones and
the original pile was רוב מנין ורוב בנין rov minyan v'rov binyan
a חצי קב. chatzi kav. That would be the case of חצי
קב, chatzi kav, so we're not just talking about random bones, it
has to be drawn from again I don't know exactly does it
mean you need a little bit of each of those bones, okay,
but it has to be coming from a type of a bone
structure, a number of bones, a quantity of bones that would itself
cause טומאת מת באוהל, tumas meis b'ohel, רוב מנין או רוב בנין.
rov minyan o rov binyan. But then תוספות Tosafos says the next
line which is important.
חצי קב chatzi kav is pretty big then I mean.
Yeah, I mean somebody if Tzvi were here he would be looking
it up.
One and a half to
two and a half quarts. One and a half to two and
a half quarts. Okay, I mean that's not so big like what's
one of those thin bottles of milk. That's like what. That's a
half a quart. What? Two liters?
Two liters?
Those thin things, it's a quart.
Okay. And what did you say? One and a half to 2.65.
2.65.
Okay. But of those big bottles of... Okay.
Okay. So then it's not such a trivial amount. Now relevant to
that, תוספות Tosfos says like this, the other point is, let me
get to the other point.
Maybe like a lot of little bones from different people. That would...
What? No. Well, we're going to get to that about different people.
No. But the basic answer is no. Now תוספות Tosfos says here,
now if you take a look go down in that תוספות, Tosfos,
the line starts with the word ורוב בנינו. v'rov binyano. Okay, you
see the line ורוב בנינו v'rov binyano like the third line. ורוב
בנינו מפרש לקמן שני שוקים, v'rov binyano mefaresh lekaman shnei shokim, either
the two hips,
או ירך אחד o yerech echad and one thigh, או איפכא o
ipcha or the opposite. Okay, now thigh bones are very big, anyway,
or hip bones are big. Anyway, ואף על פי v'af al pi
here's the part I wanted to look at, so that's the, that's
considered the most of the structure, and now ואף על פי שמטמא
באוהל ברוב הקב, v'af al pi she'metameh b'ohel b'rov ha'kav, the הלכה
halacha is actually a half that amount, half of a half, a
quarter of a
קב kav causes טומאת אוהל, tumas ohel, כדאיתא בהדיא במתניתין בפרק קמא
דאהלות, k'isa b'hedya b'matnisin b'perek kama d'Ohalos, אלו מטמאין באוהל eilu metamin
b'ohel וקחשיב רוב העצמות הבאות מרוב מנין או מרוב בנין. v'kachshiv rov
ha'atzamot ha'ba'ot mi'rov minyan o mi'rov binyan. So here's a half and
there's a quarter. מכל מקום הלכה היא שאין הנזיר מגלח אלא על
חצי קב. mikol makom halacha hee she'ein ha'nazir megaleach ela al chatzi
kav. Okay, that's the הלכה, halacha, okay, and then he dismisses another
possibility. Meaning there are some cases they seem will seem trivial because
okay, fine, there's a difference. A quarter of a קב kav טומאת
אוהל, tumas ohel, a half of a קב kav until you're מגלח.
megaleach. But there are a few cases that cause טומאת מת דאורייתא
tumas meit d'Oraisa and nevertheless we have a tradition do not lead
to נזיר מגלח, nazir megaleach, you know, unless you know, are not
נזיר מגלח. nazir megaleach. And here it's a question about a quarter
of a קב kav versus a half. We'll see some others which
have some greater relevance. Okay. So a חצי קב chatzi kav of
bones, and as תוספות Tosfos told us which come from רוב מנין
rov minyan or רוב בנין.
rov binyan. So is he now allowed
to be מטמא metameh himself? It might not
be לאו lav either. Yeah, it could be that it's not the
לאו lav either. By the כהן kohen we say אין כהן מוזהר
עליו. ein kohen muzhar olov. Okay. So a כהן kohen can actually
do, be מטמא? metameh?
Yes.
Correct, technically speaking. Okay. This is באוהל. b'ohel. This is באוהל, b'ohel,
okay. ועל חצי לוג דם, v'al chatzi log dam, and on a
half a לוג log of blood. Now that's another good example because
if you remember at the end of yesterday we said רביעית דם
revi'is dam is מטמא באוהל. metameh b'ohel. So here again רביעית דם
revi'is dam is מטמא באוהל metameh b'ohel but you need... of a
dead person, yes, but you need twice that amount in order for
the נזיר nazir to be מגלח. megaleach. So for the bones and
the blood when it comes to טומאת אוהל, tumat ohel, you need
twice the minimum amount for a נזיר nazir to be מגלח. megaleach.
So that is now what type of ways do these conduct טומאה
tuma and a נזיר nazir will be מגלח? megaleach? ועל מגען ועל
משאן ועל אהילן. v'al magaan v'al masaan v'al ahilan. Touching them, carrying
them, or being מאהיל, ma'ahil, tenting over them or having them tent
over you or being under the same roof. אוהל. ohel. So those,
that list is all types of טומאה. tuma. Now here is a
following list of things that cause טומאת מת tumas meit not through
אוהל ohel but through contact. ועל עצם כשעורה, v'al etzem k'se'ora, even
a tiny little piece of bone as small as a barley bean,
what's it called, seed, what's it called, the barley something, grain, okay,
על מגעו ועל משאו, al mada'o v'masa'o, touching and carrying it. Okay,
so here's that's something which causes טומאה. tuma. Most of the things
if they cause טומאה tuma by contact cause טומאה באוהל. tuma b'ohel.
Okay. But the basic one major difference is bones. Bones, as we
just saw, you need either the skull or the spinal cord or
the רוב מנין rov minyan or the רוב בנין rov binyan or
a certain quantity that comes from those amounts. That's for טומאת אוהל,
tumat ohel, but for touch even a tiny little chip of bone
the size of a grain of barley. Okay. And therefore that causes
טומאת מת tumas meit and therefore a נזיר nazir will shave. על
אלו הנזיר מגלח, al eilu ha'nazir megaleach, for these a נזיר nazir
will shave his head, ומזה בשלישי ובשביעי, u'ma'zeh ba'shlishi u'va'shvi'i, sprinkle the
ashes on days three and seven, סותר את הקודמין, soter es ha'kodmin,
it will destroy the earlier days, ואינו מתחיל למנות אלא עד שיטהר,
v'eino matchil limnos ela ad she'yitaher, right, and he, no, for טומאה
tuma all the earlier days. You're thinking about shaving. But for טומאה
tuma all the earlier days and he does not begin counting again
עד שיטהר מביא קרבנותיו ad she'yitaher mevi korbanosov until he becomes טהור
tahor and brings the קרבנות korbanot the next day and then starts
which is interesting that he starts counting the next day. Does he
start? Or does he? He delays bringing the קרבנות. korbanot. We can
worry about that later. But basically this is a list of the
minimum sizes of the body and parts of the body that cause
טומאת מת tumas meit and almost everything is the same minimum for
אוהל ohel and other things with the exception of bones. Bones, a
tiny bit of bone causes טומאה tuma by touch but you need
a much more significant amount to cause טומאת אוהל. tumat ohel. Okay.
And again that there are two things we identified so far that
cause טומאת מת tumas meit that a נזיר nazir is not מגלח
megaleach and that is less than a חצי קב chatzi kav of
עצמות atzamot and less than a חצי לוג chatzi log of blood.
That once it's a quarter of a, half of that amount it
causes טומאת מת tumas meit but only with that amount is
a נזיר מגלח. nazir megaleach.
That's exactly what I said. The first list was טומאת אהל, tumas
ohel, yes, yes, not that you don't have to infer it, the
first list ended with על מגען ועל משאן ועל אהילן. al magaan
v'al masaan v'al ahilan.
So you have one big list which tells you everything on this
list is caused—is caused טומאה tumah through touch, carrying and אהל, ohel,
and then there's one thing that only causes טומאה tumah through touch
and not through אהל ohel and that's a chip of bone, okay?
That's exactly what the משנה's Mishnah doing. It's constructing two lists and
telling you the first list is everything, the second list is just
through touch and carrying, not through אהל. ohel. Yes.
Am I reading the משנה Mishnah correctly that everything here as a
source of טומאה tumah comes from a מת meis except for אבר
מן החי?
eiver min hachai? Correct, yes, that is correct.
So there's a glaring exception.
Yes, and that's why I made that point. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: אחר פטירתו של רבי
מאיר, Achar petiraso shel Rabbi Meir, after רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir passed
away, אמר להם רבי יהודה לתלמידיו, amar lahem Rabbi Yehuda l'talmidav, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said to his students: אל יכנסו תלמידי רבי מאיר
לכאן, Al yichnasu talmidei Rabbi Meir l'chan, don't let רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir students into our בית מדרש, beis medrash, מפני שקנתרנים הם, mipnei
shekantranim heim, because they are troublemakers, ולא ללמוד תורה הם באים, v'lo
lilmod Torah heim ba'in, they don't have a sincere desire to learn
תורה, Torah, אלא לקפחני בהלכות הם באים, ela lekapacheini bahalachos heim ba'in,
they're trying to just like annoy me, you know, with their—in
matters of הלכה, halacha, meaning they're trying to show how brilliant they
are. Right? We've all had students like this, right? They want to,
you know, maybe they don't want to דווקא davka annoy the teacher,
but they always—often manage to do that. And they're really just interested
in the whole thing as an intellectual exercise and the mind games
and they're not really coming to like just for the sake of
like learning תורה Torah and getting to—and getting to the הלכה halacha
and getting to the answer. Okay, so don't let them in the
בית מדרש. beis medrash. Okay, so דחק סומכוס ונכנס. dachak Sumchos v'nichnas.
So סומכוס Sumchos forces his way in and he got into the
בית מדרש, beis medrash, okay? And סומכוס Sumchos was a—one of the
תלמידי מובהק talmidei muvhak of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. אמר להם, Amar
lahem, so they were learning this משנה Mishnah presumably, and presumably this
is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said, you know, a נזיר's מגלח nazir
megaleach on a כזית מן המת kezayis min hameis and סומכוס Sumchos
said, כך שנה לי רבי מאיר, kach shana li Rabbi Meir, when
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir taught me this משנה, Mishnah, here's how he
taught it to me: על אלו טומאת הנזיר מגלח על המת ועל
כזית מן המת. al eilu tumas hanazir megaleach al hameis v'al kezayis
min hameis. So he didn't just say על כזית מן המת, al
kezayis min hameis, I mean I'm explaining this based on the—on the
later discussion, it seems like this is the context. He said on
a מת meis and on a כזית מן המת. kezayis min hameis.
So כעס רבי יהודה, ka'as Rabbi Yehuda, well, כעס רבי יהודה ואמר
להם, ka'as Rabbi Yehuda v'amar lahem, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda got angry
and he said to his students: לא כך אמרתי לכם, Lo kach
amarti lachem, didn't I tell you this? אל יכנסו תלמידי רבי מאיר
לכאן, Al yichnasu talmidei Rabbi Meir l'chan, don't let רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir students into the בית מדרש. beis medrash. מפני שקנתרנים הם, Mipnei
shekantranim heim, they're troublemakers. על כזית מן המת מגלח על המת לא
כל שכן? Al kezayis min hameis megaleach al hameis lo kol shekein?
If you're מגלח megaleach on a כזית מן המת, kezayis min hameis,
why do you have to say על המת? al hameis? Now this
is very bizarre, okay, because like, alright, so it's a little bit
of a little extra phrase, this means you're a troublemaker? Now maybe
he's a troublemaker because he's giving me a hard time. I said
כזית מן המת kezayis min hameis and he's challenging me to say,
'Oh, you can't just say כזית מן המת. kezayis min hameis. You
have to first say על המת.' al hameis. It's like, why is
that—why is that important? I mean it's implicit, okay? So maybe the
troublemaker is not that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir taught על כזית מן
המת al kezayis min hameis but the insistence on saying that first.
Like, what's the point? Okay? I know it's annoying, but I'm saying
if he just said, 'Oh, my version was this,' it's like, 'Okay,
whatever.' But if he's making himself annoying about that, right? He's saying,
'You can't just say כזית מן המת, kezayis min hameis, you have
to say על המת ועל כזית מן המת.' al hameis v'al kezayis
min hameis. So it's 'What are you doing? You're just, you know,
you're just making trouble, like it's implicit, why—what difference does it make?'
Okay. Now אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yosi, so said רבי יוסי—No,
Rabbi Yosi we're not done, read the next line! אמר רבי יוסי,
Amar Rabbi Yosi, so said רבי יוסי: Rabbi Yosi: יאמרו מאיר שכב,
yomru Meir shachav, they'll say מאיר Meir passed
away, יהודה כעס, Yehuda ka'as, יהודה Yehuda got angry, יוסי שתק, Yosi
shatak, and I was silent? תורה מה תהא עליה? Torah mah tehei
aleha? What will be about תורה? Torah? Like, you know, רבי מאיר's
Rabbi Meir תורה Torah is being sort of dismissed in his death.
I have to come to defend even though I'm a student of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or a colleague of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
whatever, you know, I have to come and defend רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir honor because to defend his תורה. Torah. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar
Rabbi Yosi, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said: לא נצרכה אלא למת שאין
עליו כזית בשר. lo nitzercha ela l'meis she'ein alav kezayis basar. Now,
here's what you need it for. Let's imagine you have a dead
body that you have the entire body but there's no flesh left,
it's all just bones. So that's why you need to say על
המת. al hameis. Now that's a difficult answer because then you also—that's
implicit in the bone issue, right? Because we also mentioned a certain
amount of bones, right? So the גמרא Gemara said: ועדיין יאמר על
אבר ממנו מגלח על כולו לא כל שכן? V'adayin yomar al eiver
mimenu megaleach al kulo lo kol shekein? Okay,
but so what? If even for one limb you shave, of course
for the whole body! You didn't really answer the question. Why do
you need to
say
on the
whole body? אלא כי הא דאמר רבי יוחנן, Ela ki ha d'amar
Rabbi Yochanan, like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan taught: לא נצרכה אלא לנפל
שלא נתקשרו אבריו בגידים. lo nitzercha ela l'nefel shelo nitkashru evarav begidim.
We're talking about a—about a stillbirth that the—the sinews did not yet
develop. Develop, and because there are no גידין, gidin, we don't know
this yet, but I'm telling you, it does not have the idea
of an אבר eiver does not apply. Okay. Now, of course the
interesting thing is, fine, the idea of an אבר eiver doesn't apply.
It has bones, it has flesh apparently, but no, well it has
flesh, but it doesn't have some of the sinews have not developed.
Again, I don't know, I'm not an embryologist, I can't attest to
this. Anyway, but apparently that you don't have the טומאת אבר tumas
eiver if it doesn't have גידין, gidin, okay? So that's the case
where you could have a whole מת, mes, and if it's a
very small, very tiny embryo, it doesn't have a כזית בשר, kezayis
basar, okay? Now, what about the idea of רוב מנין, rov minyan,
רוב בנין, rov binyan, you know, שדרה, shidra, גולגולת, gulgoles, maybe that
doesn't apply when it's such a, you know, I don't know, when
does it even develop a skeletal structure? Must develop it early though,
right?
Pretty early.
Yeah. I don't know. Anyway, it's not exactly clear to me why
you don't have the idea of the שדרה shidra and גולגולת, gulgoles,
but maybe there's some assumption also that if it's that small that
doesn't apply, okay? So הכא נמי בנפל שלא נתקשרו איבריו בגידין. hacha
nami benefel shelo nitkashru eivarav begidin.
That's the case where you have it where you could have a
whole מת mes that doesn't fall into any of those other
categories. רבא אמר לא נצרכה אלא לרוב בנינו או לרוב מנינו שאין
בהן רוב עצמות, Rava amar lo nitzrecha ella lerov binyano o lerov
minyano she'ein bahen rov atzamos, okay? No, basically we can be talking
about you have the skeletal structure, so you have רוב מנין rov
minyan and רוב בנין, rov binyan, but what happens again if it's
a very small corpse, and you can have רוב מנין rov minyan
and רוב בנין, rov binyan, and you don't have the minimum quantity?
You don't have the רוב עצמות. rov atzamos. Interesting he mentions רוב
rov as opposed to the חצי קב, chatzi kav, okay? That's probably
a little לאו דוקא lav davka because the normal again טומאת אהל
tumas ohel is רובע, rova, even though here we're talking about נזיר
מגלח nazir megaleach, so it's a חצי קב. chatzi kav. So he
says you could have a case where you have no flesh, you
just have the skeleton, very small, but it's a very small skeleton,
so even though it's רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין—now rov
binyan this is interesting, right? Because we might have imagined if you
really have רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין, rov binyan, it's
not measured by quantity. Now we see that that gets back to
the תוספות Tosafot I read to you, that it's the intersection of
these two, right? You need a half of a—a quarter of a
קב kav or a half of a קב kav for רוב מנין
rov minyan or רוב בנין. rov binyan. Even if you had an
entire רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין rov binyan by itself,
uncrushed, whole, the entire thing by itself, if it were not—if it
did not have the minimum volume, it would not cause טומאת אהל.
tumat ohel. So that's important for an—well no, but apparently the same
is true in general for טומאת מת. tumat mes. The only difference
of a נזיר nazir is a רובע rova versus a חצי קב.
chatzi kav. Okay, but basically this is important, that it's not just
רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין, rov binyan, it's רוב מנין
rov minyan and רוב בנין rov binyan that also is a quarter
of a קב kav for טומאת מת, tumat mes, a half of
a קב kav for נזיר nazir מגלח, megaleach but again the interesting
thing, it's ignoring the שדרה shidra and the
גולגולת, gulgoles, so... Yes, so... A נפל nefel is a stillborn or
a miscarried... No, a
נפל's nefel a
stillborn or miscarriage,
yeah, yeah, it could even be as early as like, you know,
the 40th day, which could be how it could be very undeveloped.
Okay, but again, what's not being explored here is why these are
exceptions to a שדרה shidra and גולגולת. gulgoles. I want to say
two things about this context about this. It is interesting, it's hard
to talk about this, right? It's sort of
so objectifying and impersonal talking about these parts of a dead body.
It's interesting in this context that it starts with the story of
talking about death and talking about death in a much more sort
of euphemistic way, in a much more respectful way, right? It says
פטירה, petira, which literally means he left, right? He, you know, he
took his leave of us, right? And שכיב, shechiv, and then it
says אמר יוסי יאמר מאחר ששכב, amar Yosi yomar me'ahar shechav, which
literally meant he lay—he went to lie down, right? So both of
those are, you know, are just more, I think, dignified, don't—don't objectify
this as body parts, you know, when somebody dies, and also I
think suggest also that sense about going to a different world, going
to a different place. He's—he takes his leave of us, you know,
and there's still the soul that lives on and so on. So
it's interesting the difference, the terminologies of death that are introduced here.
The other thing though is, is that when this—this exact exchange also
appears in קידושין, Kiddushin, and there, it makes a lot more sense
for two reasons, a, literarily and b, why it's so annoying. The
משנה Mishnah in קידושין Kiddushin talks about what types of objects you
can use—a man can use to marry a woman and are they
considered איסור הנאה issur hana'ah or not. So it says that a
כהן Kohen can marry his—marry a woman by giving her the meat
of קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, like of a חטאת, chatas, you know,
that—that it has value. I mean, she can't eat it, but you
know, it has value, she could sell it back to other כהנים,
Kohanim, okay? So that's what it says, okay? בשר קדשי קדשים. basar
kodshei kodashim. Now apparently that was a משנה Mishnah of רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. So in the same way our משנה Mishnah turns out
to have been a
משנה Mishnah of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. a person can be מקדש mekadesh a wife
with בשר קדשי קדשים Basar Kodshei Kodashim So then רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda got upset and he says, like the same thing, "Didn't I
tell you, don't let רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's student in here?" He
says, "What is a woman doing in the עזרה Azara in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash that they're doing a קידושין Kiddushin ceremony right
there in the עזרה Azara So there you understand it's like, you
understand what bothered him. It's like, he said like this isn't like
real הלכה Halacha these are like mind games, right? So we don't
want to talk about like practical הלכה Halacha you just want to
explore interesting theoretical absurd types of ideas. So you a little bit
more understand what bothered him. But what's particularly cute about that גמרא
Gemara is then the גמרא Gemara gives a whole series of answers
about how a woman could be in the עזרה Azara By the
way, it's interesting because a woman is not not allowed in the
עזרה Azara as תוספות Tosafot demonstrates. So the question is not so
much that she's not allowed, but it would be unusual for her
to be there for not the purpose of bringing a קרבן Korban
or, you know, inappropriate for her to be there and to be
doing an act of קידושין Kiddushin although then it's not so much
about the woman, it's about doing an act of קידושין Kiddushin in
the עזרה Azara But anyway, but תוספות Tosafot says that she's not
allowed, but it would not happen, you know, would not be expected
and it would not be usual for her to do... Right, right.
Anyway, anyway, but it's like an absurd scenario is what's being said,
not that it's forbidden. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara has a whole
series of answers. So one answer is, well, maybe the כהן Kohen
is giving it to her father, and he's marrying off his daughter.
Or maybe she made a שליח Shaliach and he's accepting it for
her in the עזרה Azara And then the final answer was, the
final answer was דחקה ונכנסה מאי Dachka venichnesa mai
maybe she just forced her way into the עזרה Azara which plays
off on the beginning of the story, which is סומכוס Sumchus was
דחק ונכנס Dachak venichnas So it seems there that there this literary
construct really comes from that case, both why he got upset and
also the whole דחק ונכנס Dachak venichnas you know, and the absurdity
of the scenarios really sort of shows like what this means that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is like playing these mind games and they're
not just coming for הלכה Halacha Yes, it's very searching.
Where's that סוגיא Sugya
It's נב
עמוד ב
Nun
Bet Amud Bet in מה?
Mah? קידושין Kiddushin נב Nun Bet Yeah. Okay. Secondly, if you see
nothing has changed, the Jews, you could rent the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash for a wedding. Exactly. Exactly.
Look at the first רש"י Rashi on on the גמרא Gemara here,
right there, yeah.
גץ וצורי Getz vetzuri It's
like cognate of terror, like the terrorized?
Really? Oh, that's interesting. Okay. Yes. Exactly. Exactly. This...
רבי מאיר שכב ורבי יהודה כעס ורבי יוסי שתק Rabbi Meir shachav
v'Rabbi Yehuda kaas v'Rabbi Yosi shatak
is really saying that they they've gotten too personal about it. You
know, everybody's thinking what will Rabbi so-and-so say? That the personalities are
what's the
important thing, and
not the important thing is
the הלכה Halacha or what's being... Ah, that's very nice. Right. That's
very, very nice. יישר כח Yasher koach Everybody hear the point Dovid
made? He said the point about, you know, מאיר שכב יהודה כעס
יוסי שתק Meir shachav Yehuda kaas Yosi shatak is that it will
all lead to a discussion about the people and the personalities and
we're forgetting the תורה Torah that's being taught, and it's really sort
of a reorienting to the תורה Torah which is really what's important
about all of this. יישר כח Yasher koach Okay, now we go
on. כזית מן המת כזית נצל Kezayis min hamet kezayis netzel So
now we move, a כזית kezayis of the corpse, which is basically
the flesh, and a כזית kezayis of this נצל netzel which is
some type of dissolved and recongealed flesh, thank you. So it says,
ואיזו נצל ve'eizu netzel what is this נצל netzel בשר המת שקרש
basar hamet shekarash so the flesh of a dead body that has
congealed, but obviously first had liquefied and then it
congealed. ומהל שהרתיח umohal she'hirtiach and also some type of a juices,
I can't say it any other way, that ran off from the
flesh that then were like boiled and congealed. Now the question is
why does it say boiled? So I'll get back to that in
a minute, but the גמרא Gemara is going to focus on the
first phrase. Let's take a look. Okay,
okay.
So those are two versions of נצל netzel So one it seems
like it just naturally congeals and the other maybe it congealed through
boiling, one maybe more was flesh that had liquefied, the other more
just the juices themselves that ran off. היכי דמי heichi dami Now
what's the case? It starts with the issue about the בשר basar
אילימא דלא ידיענא דדידיה הוא ilima delo yediana dedidei hu if we
don't know that this we have this congealed thing and we don't
know where it came from, did it come from the body or
not? כי קריש מאי הוי ki karash mai havay So, solidifying, meaning
doesn't mean anything. Now תוספות'ס Tosafot's point about this... no, גמרא'ס Gemara's
דדידיה הוא dedidei hu is it his? I mean, who else's? We'll
see in a minute in the גמרא Gemara it means, did it
come from the flesh or maybe it came from other types of
liquids that are running off of the body, like, for example, the
spit or the or the mucus or other types of liquids that
are not the flesh? So if we don't know if it's congealed
flesh, then congealing shouldn't tell us anything.
And those liquids are not מטמא metamei
Those liquids are not
מטמא metamei So or certainly not טומאת מת tumas meis or whatever,
they might be indirect because they are in contact with the dead,
but they're not the... themselves the dead. Okay, so אלא דידעינן דדידהו.
ella diyadinan dedidehu. So we know that it was the flesh that
had dissolved and recongealed. אף על גב דלא קרש, af al gav
dela karash, so he needs it to congeal, meaning now you could
have said, why not? Meaning who knows, maybe if it's all in
liquid form, you know, I don't know what these הלכות halachos are,
maybe if it's in liquid form that's not considered flesh, maybe it
has to be in solid form. But the גמרא Gemara takes it
for granted that it is. So even if it was in dissolved
form, once it was actually coming from the flesh, it should cause
the same טומאה. tumah. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara's answer
is. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי ירמיה בסתם. Amar Rabi
Yirmeya bistam. We don't know what the nature of this congealed liquid
is. Okay, אי קרש, i karash, I mean obviously it came from
the body. אי קרש, i karash, if it congealed, מוחל הוא. mochal
hu. So then we know that it is juices from the flesh
and therefore it represents the flesh and that's why it's מטמא metamei
in an amount of a כזית. kezayis. לא קרש, lo karash, if
it doesn't congeal, then דילמא כיחו וניעו הוא, dilma keicho venio hu,
maybe it's spit and it's mucus and therefore we don't know. So
basically the גמרא Gemara which is מחדש mechadesh that you don't really
need it to congeal, basically it doesn't matter what form it's in,
but dissolved flesh or the juices that run off of the flesh
are מטמא metamei like the flesh itself and this issue of congealing
is only to determine what its identity is. תוספות Tosafos says that's
the same about the second point, about this here טיאח, tiach, boiling,
whatever that means, if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות
Tosafos says, אמר רבי ירמיה בסתם, Amar Rabi Yirmeya bistam, so he
says, כלומר דידעינן דבא מזה המת, kelomar diyadinan deba mi-zeh hameis, we
know it came from the body, אבל לא ידעינן מוחל זה מבשרו
או מכיחו וקיבעו, aval lo yadinan mochal zeh mivesaro o mikeicho vekivo,
או
מכיחו, o mikeicho, we don't know what the source of this liquid
was from the body. קירש ודאי מוחל הוא הבא מבשר המת, kirash
vadai mochal hu haba mibesar hameis, if it's still, if it, if
it congeals then it's definitely like from the juices of the flesh
or from a dissolved flesh or the juices of the flesh. ואילו
לא קרש כיחו וניעו הוא. ve'ilo lo karash keicho venio hu. And
then he says והכי נמי יש לפרש גבי הרתיח דלא ידעינן, vehachi
nami yesh lefaresh gabi hirtiach delo yadinan, it could be, the גמרא
Gemara never deals with the הרתיח hirtiach case, but תוספות Tosafos says
we'll assume the same. Okay? That you basically have some juices that
then and you don't know what type of, what they are, whether
they're from the flesh or other where, or some where, or from
the mucus. וכי הרתיח דעבר רתיחות ודאי מוחל הבא מהמת הוא. vechi
hirtiach de'avar ritchus vadai mochal haba me-hameis hu.
And if it gets boiled and it starts, I don't know, you
know, like bubbling or whatever, then you know that it's from the
flesh. וזהו נצל. vezehu netzel. לא הרתיח כיחו וניעו הוא. lo hirtiach
keicho venio hu. I have to tell you I don't really understand
that. כיחו keicho is the like the, the spit, the phlegm, phlegm,
yeah. But I have to tell you that I don't really understand
that because why can't, I mean any liquid you could boil. It's
one thing to say it's not able to congeal by itself. I
don't get the exact boiling as a test of what its nature
is. But תוספות Tosafos anyway tries to fit that into the same
pattern of the גמרא. Gemara. So the basic upshot about this is
is that if it's juices from the flesh, then and we know
what its identity is, then it's also מטמא metamei like the flesh
itself. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, a little less
graphic now. בעי מיניה אביי מרבה, ba'ei minei Abaye me-Raba, אביי Abaye
asked רבה. Raba. I mean it's not so much less graphic, but
anyway, יש נצל לבהמה או אין נצל לבהמה. yesh netzel lebeheimah o
ein netzel lebeheimah. This idea that juices from the flesh count like
the flesh itself, does this apply to other areas of טומאה tumah
in addition to טומאת מת? tumas meis? Maybe it's a matter of
definition of flesh and therefore we should apply it in other areas
outside of טומאת מת, tumas meis, like טומאת נבילה. tumas neveilah. Okay,
if you have a כזית kezayis of a dead animal corpse of
the flesh, it causes טומאה, tumah, not טומאת מת, tumas meis, it's
not relevant for a נזיר, nazir, we're no longer dealing with a
נזיר, nazir, נזיר nazir can touch dead animal corpses, fine. The carcasses,
that's not our issue. Our issue is does it cause טומאה tumah
if it's not the actual flesh but it's the juices from the
flesh? If it's liquefied or it's the juices that ran off.
יש נצל לבהמה או אין נצל לבהמה. yesh netzel lebeheimah o ein
netzel lebeheimah. מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we say גמירי נצל דאתי
מאדם, gmiri netzel d'ati mi-adam,
our tradition is נצל netzel that comes from a human, so it's
a הלכה halacha in טומאת מת, tumas meis, it's not a general
definition of flesh, אבל דאתי מבהמה לא, aval d'ati mibeheimah lo, but
it wouldn't apply to like,
what do you call it, carcasses of animals, או דילמא, o dilma,
or do we say לא שנא, lo shna, it won't matter, then
it also applies to carcasses of animals, it generally, it's a statement
that the juices from the flesh count as the flesh. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now this question is really moot
depending on another question. הניחא למאן דאמר טומאה חמורה עד לגר וטומאה
קלה עד לכלב שפיר. hani-cha leman d'amar tumah chamurah ad lager vetumah
kalah ad lekelev shapir. If you say weighty טומאה tumah is measured
by being until the threshold of a stranger of the and the
light טומאה tumah by the by the dog, then it makes sense.
Well that was a clear enough phrase. Okay, so what does that
mean? What it means is the following.
The גמרא Gemara can sometimes pack a lot into a little phrase.
So it means the following. When it speaks about the טומאה tumah
of a of a carcass, it says, לגר אשר בשעריך תתננה ואכלה.
lager asher bish'arecha titnenah ve'achalcha. You can't eat this נבילה, neveilah, give
it to the גר, ger, to the stranger in your land, and
let him eat this נבילה, neveilah, you as a Jew cannot eat
this נבילה. neveilah. Okay, and from there we learn a purpose, הראוי
לגר קרוי נבילה שאינו ראוי לגר אינו קרוי נבילה. haraui lager karui
neveilah she'eino raui lager eino karui neveilah. That it's only considered a
נבילה neveilah if it's edible. גר ger we don't think that non-Jews
have different eating patterns than Jews or, you know,
taste buds, but that's the example in the
תורה. Torah. human consumption does it lose its status as forbidden food?
And it also can be relevant for laws of טומאה, tumah, when
it becomes not fit for human consumption, does it stop being a
source of טומאה? tumah? So that's when it says טומאה חמורה עד
לגר tumah chamurah ad lager means weighty טומאה, tumah, the carcass of
an animal that is an אב av and a source of טומאה,
tumah, it will stop having that power once it is no longer
fit for being eaten by a human being. Now that's strange because
a lot of טומאות tumot have nothing to do with food, with
being food, right? A corpse of a human being, זב, zav, נדה,
niddah, מצורע, metzora,
like most אבות הטומאות avot hatumot are not because of their identity
as food. Now you could still say if it's no longer fit
for consumption it means that somehow it's transformed significantly enough, but it's
still strange that we use as the measuring stick
edibility. But that would be the idea, that at least when it
comes to טומאת נבלה, tumat neveilah, which is a carcass of an
animal which would be eaten usually and nevertheless is a source of
טומאה, tumah, that there it loses that status once it's no longer
fit for human consumption. That's טומאה חמורה עד לגר. tumah chamurah ad
lager. Now טומאה קלה עד לכלב, tumah kalah ad lekelev, what does
that mean? Not when it's an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, but when
something gets טומאה tumah from something else. What types of things can
conduct טומאה tumah from other things? Humans, vessels, and anybody know the
third category? Food. So food that conducts טומאה tumah from elsewhere, what
is the minimum standard of food to define it as food that
it conducts טומאה tumah when it touches something else? Is it ראוי
לאכילת אדם raui leachilat adam or ראוי לאכילת כלב? raui leachilat kelev?
Okay, these phrases might be familiar with you with הלכות פסח, hilchot
Pesach, right? These are broader questions about different areas might have different
definitions of what defines something as food. Okay, so if טומאה חמורה
עד לגר tumah chamurah ad lager means it stops being a נבלה
neveilah when it's no longer fit for human consumption and having the
טומאת נבלה. tumat neveilah. טומאה קלה עד לכלב tumah kalah ad lekelev
is really a parenthetical statement completely irrelevant to us, but it's part
of the phrase, so the whole phrase was quoted and means when
it comes to something being food to conduct טומאה tumah elsewhere, it
might be enough that it's fit for being eaten by dogs. But
to have the weight of being a source of טומאה, tumah, particularly
when you're talking about something like a נבלה, neveilah, right, then it's
only if it is fit for human consumption. And again it's ironic
because most טומאות tumot have nothing to do with their edibility, but
at least by נבלה neveilah we're saying until it's fit for human
consumption. So if you say that, then he says the question is
moot. Why is the question moot? Because these juices that run off
the flesh, he's assuming are not fit for human consumption, right? Which
is funny because you think about when you cut into your steak
and the juices run off and whatever, you know, people mop it
up with their bread. Am I talking to some vegans here?
It's on a decomposing side. Right, it's decomposing.
Yes, but we are talking about dead animals. Okay, I do realize,
I'm sorry, liquefication of flesh. Right, so the difference might be it
has a different smell.
Exactly, exactly. This might not be right just like the meat on
your plate, right, it is as the body decomposes. So the assumption
is that the juices that run off from the flesh as the
body decomposes are not fit for human consumption. And therefore it says
whether you say it has a status of the flesh or not,
it's a moot point because when we're dealing with the טומאה tumah
of נבלה, neveilah, right, other טומאות tumot are not about fit for
consumption, טומאת מת tumat meit is not about fit for, but when
we're dealing with נבלה neveilah it's about fit for consumption. So therefore
it's really a moot question
whether the liquids have a status of flesh, they're not fit for
human consumption, end of story. Okay, so let's read that again. הני
למאן דאמר טומאה חמורה עד לגר, hani leman de'amar tumah chamurah ad
lager, when it comes to the weighty, the נבלה, neveilah, it has
to be fit for human consumption. טומאה קלה עד לכלב, tumah kalah
ad lekelev, other types of food טומאות tumot fit for dogs, so
that's parenthetical. שפיר, shapir, then that makes sense, meaning it's a moot
point because these juices are not fit for human consumption, end of
story. Okay, אלא למאן דאמר טומאה חמורה עד לכלב, ela leman de'amar
tumah chamurah ad lekelev, but according to the approach that says even
for a נבלה, neveilah, it doesn't have to be human consumption, it
just only has to be consumable by a dog. Okay, again, still
we're still using a definition of food by נבלה neveilah that we
don't use by other טומאות, tumot, but by a dog is enough.
So if that's true, so that's then that's my question. These juices
presumably are edible by a dog, do they have a status of
meat or not? Okay, that's the question.
Of טומאה, tumah, right.
Right, so do we say אלא למאן דאמר טומאה חמורה עד לכלב
מאי איכא למימר, ela leman de'amar tumah chamurah ad lekelev mai ika
lemeimar, what's the story? תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. המחו
באור טמא בחמה טהור. himchu ba'ur tamei bechamah tahor. You have this
נבלה neveilah and you go ahead and
dissolve it over a fire, you liquefy it over a fire, okay,
then it is טמא. tamei. If however you let
it rot
and liquefy... When you put it out on the fire, presumably it's
not getting putrefied. Okay, so ואי סלקא דעתך עד לכלב, vei salka
dachtech ad lekelev, and if you said that something
remains טמא tamei as long as it's fit, נבילה neveilah remains טמא
tamei as long as it's fit for a dog, אפילו בחמה נמי,
afilu bechama nami, so it's assumed that even in the sun, it
should remain fit for a dog. So this doesn't actually prove, answer
our question. All that's being demonstrated by this is that presumably the
difference here, it's assuming that something that
liquefied by being left in the sun is fit for a dog,
okay, and it's saying that it's טהור. tahor. So it proves one
way or another the liquids are טהור, tahor, either because you need
ראוי לאדם rauy leadam or because the liquids aren't defined as the
meat. Okay, but if the liquids when left out in the sun
is טהור, tahor, the Gemara's assuming you see you need ראוי לאדם,
rauy leadam, because if the ראוי לכלב rauy lekelev was enough and
it was considered for meat even when it liquefied, it should be
טמא. tamei. So the Gemara says no, the Gemara says no, ואי
סלקא דעתך עד לכלב אפילו בחמה נמי.
vei salka dachtech ad lekelev
afilu bechama nami. Gemara says no. אימת מנחי לה? eimat manchi lei?
No, no, no, says the Gemara, no,
when you leave it out on the sun, when does it sort
of liquefy? בתר דאסרח, batar deasrach, after it putrefies. So בחמה כיון
דאסרח הוי ליה עפר. bechama kivan deasrach havei lei afar. If you
leave it out on the sun after it's putrefied, it's spoiled, it's
like dust, meaning it's not even ראוי לכלב. rauy lekelev. Okay, and
that thankfully is the end of that discussion. Okay, so the question
was: is the liquefied flesh of an animal considered טומאת נבילה, tumat
neveilah, meat for טומאת נבילה? tumat neveilah? In order to answer that
question, we would have to assume you don't need ראוי לאדם, rauy
leadam, and we don't know the answer whether or not you need
ראוי לאדם. rauy leadam. And the one משנה, mishna, actually תוספתא, tosefta,
that some is relevant and talks about liquefying, it could be seen
as saying it's טהור tahor because it's not ראוי לאדם, rauy leadam,
but then because that's what happens when you leave it out in
the sun. But the Gemara comes back and says no, that might
be טהור tahor because it's not ראוי לכלב. rauy lekelev. And maybe
when it's ראוי לכלב rauy lekelev and not ראוי לאדם, rauy leadam,
maybe your question is still relevant. Okay, and we in the end
don't know the answer to that question. Now we get to another
one which is a lot more pleasant. Let's take a look. תנן.
tenan. So we're going to introduce this next conversation by starting with
a משנה mishna in מכשירין.
machshirin. Is that the conclusion here that it is ראוי לכלב? rauy
lekelev?
No, no, no, it just the conclusion is that if it's left
out in the sun, it's not
ראוי לכלב, rauy lekelev, and we don't really have a conclusion about
what would be about the הלכה halacha if it were ראוי לכלב.
rauy lekelev. Okay, now we have a משנה. mishna. כל הניצוק טהור.
kol hanitzok tahor. All pouring things are טהור. tahor. Now what it
means is the following. I have something
טמא tamei here, let's take about a carcass of a dead animal,
and I'm pouring water on the carcass. So water that hits the
animal is טמא, tamei, right? It's a ראשון rishon because it's in
contact with that. What about the water that's still in my jug
up here? Do we say that it's all connected in one unit?
Like if I touch the animal with a stick, it wouldn't just
be the tip of the stick would be טמא, tamei, the whole
stick would be טמא. tamei. So how about this connection through being
poured? Does that make it one object or not? And the answer
is no, it's not one object. כל הניצוק טהור. kol hanitzok tahor.
It doesn't mean the stuff that hit, but it means being in
the process of being poured, it remains טהור. tahor. Only the stuff
that actually touches is טמא. tamei. Okay, it's not one object. חוץ,
chutz, with the exception מדבש הזיפים, midevash hazifim, from דבש devash of
זיפים, zifim, which is possibly a place, or Tosafot says something else
about what it might mean.
Oh, it just is a very thick type of a honey, if
I just refer to its thickness. Okay, which basically is a very,
very thick honey. והצפיחית, vehatzapichit, which Tosafot says could mean like the
cakes of honey that come straight out of the beehive. Those are
so thick that they actually are considered more like a solid. Now
it's an interesting question, somebody told me that somebody once asked Rav
Moshe about, you know,
about Jell-O. Is it a liquid or a solid? I think it
was pertaining to, I'm trying to remember what the question was, it
might have been like the minimum שיעור shiur for a ברכה אחרונה
beracha achrona or something. Do you go by כזית kezayit or רביעית
revi'it or whatever? So he said, so he said, yeah, I can't
figure that one out either. So it's sort of like the liquid
crystal question. Okay, so anyway, so is it... okay, so the really
thick honey, really thick honey is a solid. בית שמאי אומרים, Beit
Shammai omrim, or it's not a solid, but it's enough that it's
seen as one object. בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim, אף המקפה
של גריסין ושל פול, af hamikpah shel gerisin veshel pol, even
certain types of oatmeal of lentils is considered like really thick, and
therefore if you're pouring it onto let's say this carcass, then the
whole thing becomes
טמא tamei מפני שהיא סולדת לאחוריה, mipnei shehi soledet leachoreha, because it
pulls back. What does it mean it pulls back? It means that
if you were to like stop the pouring, okay, it wouldn't be
if you're pouring... liquid and you turn up like that, everything that's
out of your cup is going to fall to the ground, right?
But if you're turning something else that's like really thick and it's,
you know, I guess viscous or whatever, if you pull it then
some of it stays back with you, it doesn't all go away.
So that shows that it's more connected. By the way the phrase
סולדת, soledes, which means to like retract backwards, is relevant for the
שיעור shiur of יד סולדת בו, yad soledes bo, right, which is
the which is the
how hot a certain liquids have to be to be considered cooking,
trans-cooked, so you recoil, you touch it and you recoil back. Okay.
So by רמי בר חמא, Rami bar Chama, and רמי בר חמא,
Rami bar Chama, that's the משנה. Mishnah. Now we're going to ask
our question. יש ניצוק לאוכלין או אין ניצוק לאוכלין. yesh nitzok l'ochlin
o ein nitzok l'ochlin. Now you can obviously understand where this question
is being informed based on our משנה, Mishnah, but again, let's start
with it: is there ניצוק, nitzok, is it when for foods, let's
say you took something that started as a food, okay, and you
liquefied it, all right, you went ahead and you took, I mean,
you could either do it I guess by cooking it or you
took your your chicken and you put it in your food processor,
vroom, and you made it into some thick mass, some thick liquefied
type of a food. Okay, and then you poured it on a
מת, meis, okay, or on a נבלה, neveilah, okay, what would be
the הלכה? halacha?
Would that be considered to be connected or not connected? Okay. I
want to point out the
sound you made was an immersion blender and not really a food
processor. Okay. Alright. מי אמינא, Mi amina, do we say, מי אמינא,
mi amina, משום דאית בהו רירי, mishum d'is behu riri, והני לית
בהו רירי, v'hani leis behu riri, the reason for the things mentioned
mentioned earlier, whether it is the honey for the חכמים Chachamim or
the or the oatmeal for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, is because they
have רירי, riri, and רירין riri'in are like tentacles. How do they
describe רירי? riri? It's like things that actually it's not just thick,
but it's like it adheres, what do they... Thick strands that string
back. Thick strands that string back, okay, fine. That's a good one-word
for it.
I like tentacles, that's good.
Anyway, anyway, is that why, משום דאית בהו רירין, mishum d'is behu
riri'in, okay, והני לית בהו רירין, v'hani leis behu riri'in, this, even
though it's like really, really thick, your your mash, you know, your
liquid, your whatever, your pulverized chicken, it doesn't have any of these
like sticky sticky components. Right? או דילמא משום דסמיכי, O dilma mishum
d'smichi, or is it because of its thickness? That even if it
doesn't have this idea to pull back and be connected, but
but just being very thick is enough to define as a food.
והא הכא סמיכי, V'ha hacha smichi, and here it's thick. Now just
to tell you what the where the גמרא's Gemara going to go,
it says for בית שמאי Beis Shammai it's clear that the idea
is this רירי, riri, because בית שמאי Beis Shammai talk about the
fact that if you were to stop stop it, some of it
would pull back. Okay, but the question is according to בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that mentions just
for honey. Do they also agree that it needs to be able
to be pulled back? And בית שמאי Beis Shammai just says, you
know, you know, even stuffing that's not as sticky as honey can
also, but they're all agreeing that the criteria is this idea of
רירי, riri, that some of it sticks back. או, O, or is
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma saying it's not about sticking back at
all? It's about thickness, okay, very, very thick. So maybe your בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, your oatmeal isn't thick enough, and we don't care
about the sticky factor, what we care about is the thickness factor.
So that's the גמרא's Gemara question. According to the תנא קמא, Tanna
Kamma, בית שמאי Beis Shammai it's clear that the sticky factor is
important. But according to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, maybe just the
thickness is what's key. So let's take a look. So what's the
story? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear.
חלב המת Cheilev ha'meis שהוא שלם, she'hu shaleim, you have the actual
fat of a dead body, which is full, which is whole, it's
the minimum amount minimum amount that's necessary for טומאה. tumah. Okay, והתיכו,
v'hisicho, and then it was liquefied. טמא, Tamei, it remains טמא. tamei.
Okay, even in its liquefied form. היה מפורד והתיכו, Hayah mefurad v'hisicho,
if it were separate, if you didn't have a minimum amount and
you were separate into pieces and then you liquefied it and put
it all together. טהור, Tahor, it's טהור. tahor. Now the reason for
that, the second part is not relevant for us. The reason for
that is general question, which is if something loses its טומאה tumah
because it has less than a minimum size, can it regain that
טומאה tumah once you have the minimum size? You took a כזית
kezayis of a מת, meis, and you separated it off into two
halves, right? As a physical object, neither one has enough. Okay, so
if I were to touch it, I'd be טהור. tahor. What what
if I went ahead, I put them back together and I touch
it? Am I טמא tamei or not? So that's a question. Okay,
this is assuming that you would not be טמא tamei in that
case. Now, תוספות Tosafos points out, and this is very complicated, that
there are other cases where it actually seems that you are טמא.
tamei. So תוספות Tosafos actually says it depends how the טומאה's tumah
being conducted. If those two חצי כזיתים chatzi kezaysim of a מת
meis are under a same tent, you don't have to consider them
to be one object, or let's put it this way, the act
of the tent being on top of them is sort of like
seen as like one act. And therefore in that case, you would
be טמא. tamei. But if they were two halves, when they were
two halves for me to be טמא tamei through touching
Because once it's physically different pieces, it's seen as separate acts of
touching. So therefore maybe then even after I combine them and I
touch them, I will still be טהור tahor through touch. All right?
So that's just to give you a little footnote on this. It's
very complicated, this idea of when they get separated and recombined, will
you become טמא tamei again? This משנה Mishna is assuming that at
least for touch purposes or whatever, you will not. That's the idea
if it was separated and recombined. We're not interested in the separated
and recombined. We're interested in when it was whole and liquefied, it
remains טמא. tamei. Okay, now how is that relevant for us? Let's
take a look.
It says, ואי סלקא דעתך אין ניצוק לאוכלין, ve'i salka daitach ein
nitzok le'ochlin, if you would think that things that were food, again
this חלב chelev is being considered like food, it started off as
a solid, and you would say that it's not considered combined, you
know, and one unit when it becomes liquefied, so שלם ונתכו נמי
יטהר, shaleim venitko nami yiteher, you should be טהור tahor if it's
liquefied, because even once it's liquefied, now here's a surprising thing, right?
Which is, it's one thing if I am pouring something to say
that the stuff at the top is טהור. tahor. Let's say I'm
not pouring something. Let's say I've got my cup of coffee here
and some מצורע metzora touches it, or right, some type of a
נבילה neveila touches it. What's the story about the coffee at the
bottom, right?
So what would you say there? Would there be something in us
that I think more naturally would be inclined to say, well that's
one unit. Oh damn it, sorry. You'll have to edit that out.
Okay, can somebody get me a towel?
Is there a paper towel?
Oh god. I knew I should not use a full cup of
coffee for that demonstration. Oh darn.
You need more
towels? Yes, just about, okay. All right, it shows that the גמרא
Gemara is being used. All right, anyway, so now we see that
that was a purposeful demonstration to show that coffee is not one
unit. Because only some of the coffee, notice how only some of
the coffee came out there. Anyway, so that was stupid of me,
thank you. That was really stupid of me. Anyway, so, thank you.
Anyway, so, okay. So, the point being that this is assuming, now
that we've demonstrated it, this is assuming that even in a cup,
even in one container, if we say that liquid is not combined,
then that would be true about the liquid at the bottom of
the container. You touch the liquid at the top of the container,
the liquid at the bottom of the container is not טמא, tamei,
okay? Because liquid is not combined, doesn't matter if you're pouring it
or doesn't matter if it's all in a cup. So now the
question is, the person took this fat and dissolved it, and then
they touch the fat, right? And they say it's a source of
טומאה. tumah. But if it's not combined, they're not touching the full
amount. Some of the fat is at the bottom of the container,
and some of the fat is at the top of the container,
right? The liquefied fat. The liquefied fat.
Are you dealing only with liquids? Like shouldn't the bottom of this
all liquid, shouldn't the bottom be included if it's all one?
Well that's exactly what I was saying, that what this גמרא Gemara
is showing you is that the issue about liquid not being one
unit is not only when you're pouring the liquid. Even if it's
stable and in a cup, it's not considered one unit. That's the
assumption here. And therefore it says that if you basically have liquefied
this, right? So then why does it remain a source of טומאה?
tumah? It's not all combined as one unit, right? It's become liquid
now.
Is that counter-intuitive?
It is counter-intuitive. I mean normally we talk about ניצוק nitzok actually
being poured, okay? It is true because you know I mean so
that is true that normally you think it's the fact it's being
poured that makes you sort of see them as separate. Now it
could be תוספות Tosfot tries to discuss that maybe what's going on
here is some assumption that somehow a little piece separated in the
cooking, like I don't know, splattered out and then recombined. So maybe
that's part of the idea. It's not exactly clear. Let's read the
conclusion.
But they're arguing right now to this moment it's considering
אין ניצוק לאוכלין ein nitzok le'ochlin
and so why is this all one unit?
Because if you're pouring it it could be stable in the cup.
That's what it seems to be, which is very right.
So in other words it's just a bunch of infinite number of
little drops and not one.
That is what it seems. So let's read it. I mean so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. So says אמר רב זירא, amar
Rav Zeira, so let's just finish get to the answer, אנא ומר
בריה דרב אבינא תרגימנא, ana uMar breih deRav Avina targimna, I and
the son of Rav Avina explained it, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bamai
askinan, what are we talking about? כגון דבהדי דמרתח ליה, kegon debehadei
demartach lei, as you're liquefying it, סליק עמודא דנורא לפומא דמנא, salik
amuda denura lefuma demana, the fire, the flame of fire sort of
reached the opening of the vessel that you were cooking it in,
וקרש, vekarash, and it congealed it, דאיכא כולה גבי הדדי, de'ika kula
gabei hadadi, that it's all sort of congealed and together. And therefore
in that case, we're not talking that it's really fully liquefied, which
is of course not the פשט. pshat. The פשט pshat says you
liquefied it and he's saying yeah, but in the process of liquefying
it it also re- solidified.
So that's his answer. If you remove the
fire, no. בהדי דסליק, be-hadei de-salik, no, while you're cooking it סליק,
salik, the flame of fire leapt up, rose up, and burnt the
and got to the opening of the vessel and caused it all
to really to solidify.
That doesn't make sense.
Why? How can it solidify?
That's why I read סליק. salik.
No, the heat of the fire can cause the liquid to, no,
I guess if it burns it and it chars it or something.
Do you mean like the more, sometimes like things get thicker the
more you heat them up?
Something like that.
Like pudding and
stuff that happens
at the top of—right.
Alright, let's just read the last answer. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי,
Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, תא שמע, Ta shma, so we're going to still try
to answer this question. בית שמאי אומרים אף המקוה של גריסין ושל
פול משהן סולדין לאחוריהן. Beit Shammai omrim af hamikveh shel grissin veshel
pol mi-she-hen soladin leachoreihen. So you see from בית שמאי Beit Shammai
the reason it's combined is because it pulls back and it's sticky.
Okay. So you see that it's about being, not about being thick,
but about being sticky. So the גמרא Gemara says מידי איריא? midi
irya? Is that relevant? התם משום דסמיכין, Hasam mishum desmichin, הכא משום
רירי. hacha mishum riri. Yes, there, meaning we're talking, meaning בית שמאי's
Beit Shammai issue is about the רירי, riri, is about the stickiness
factor. But we're asking about maybe the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is
not about that. I mean it's funny to read this into the
words, but essentially the answer is sure, for בית שמאי Beit Shammai
it's about the stickiness. But who knows what the honey is for
the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? Is it about stickiness or is it
about thickness? So therefore in the end of the day we don't
know for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma what is the story if
something is very, very thick but not sticky. It certainly sounds like
it's about its stickiness because honey is also sticky. So it's hard
to imagine that it's just about thickness, but the גמרא Gemara leaves
that as an unanswered question. Okay.